Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Your Majesties, Lady Cao is here with Princess Wenyi.
I hope they didn't feel unwell
walking under the the blazing sun.
Show her in quickly.
Grace to Your Majesties.
It's scorching hot at this time.
Why did you go out with the princess?
Can she handle the heat even if you can stand it?
I do apologize, Your Majesty.
The princess has been crying for the entire morning.
I thought she must be missing Her Majesty.
[The empress is the nominal mother of all imperial children.]
No worries, I miss Wenyi as well.
Come here, I'll hold her.
She seems to have lost weight from last time.
The summer heat spoils her appetite.
She hasn't been eating well lately.
Wenyi is vulnerable to the heat.
I'm afraid the concubines are struggling as well.
How about we move to the
Summer Palace to escape the heat?
The Summer Palace is well maintained.
Your Majesty can depart at any time.
I'd like to stay there for some time.
I haven't been there for 2 years
due to the mourning period for the prior emperor.
Moving is not going to be too difficult.
But the Summer Palace cannot accommodate all the concubines?
Which ones would Your Majesty go with?
They two are out of question.
Mothers of the princes and princesses
will follow to take care of the children.
And Concubine Estime.
That will be all.
Consort Honnête is in poor health.
She should go with us for her recovery.
(sigh) Of course.
As for Consort Fleur ...
I suggest she stay to take care of the palace.
This hairpin ...
I remember this is my gist for Consort Fleur.
Yes,
the princess is always happy to see
Her Highness wearing this hairpin.
So Her Highness gave it to me to play with Wenyi.
Consort Fleur is going as well.
Certainly.
Who was the thoughtful mind
to have arranged all this for me?
His Majesty wished to have your room scented
without burning incense on such a hot day.
At His Majesty's behest, we arranged
flowers and the rotating fan for you, My Lady.
What a sweet and cooling breeze!
The rotating fan is exclusive for you
among all the concubines, My Lady.
What an ingenious design!
His Majesty devoted so much thought to it.
During the canicular days [hottest period of the year],
ice will be sent to your chamber from the ice house.
It will waft coolness to your heart's delight.
His Majesty ordered us to send you ice
immediately you feel hot, My Lady.
We will make the utmost effort
to accommodate your needs, My Lady.
Thank you for your hard work, Mr Huang.
May I trouble you to inform His Majesty that
I will visit him shortly to thank him in person?
With the greatest pleasure, My Lady.
But I'm afraid His Majesty
is going to practice mounted archery.
You might want to go at a later time, My Lady.
Mounted archery?
Who did His Majesty go with?
Noble Prince Guo and Lady Cao.
Lady Cao?
Princess Wenyi has been feeling better.
His Majesty wished to see her.
His Majesty is very fond of the Summer Palace.
I'm excited to be here for the first time.
My Lady, I heard that Consort Honnête came as well.
I wonder what Her Highness looks like.
Consort Honnête has been bed-ridden for years.
We will get to see her sooner or later.
What is it?
What exceptional archery!
The wild pigeons in west Beijing are known for their swiftness.
But the archer caught two pigeons with one shot.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Is it His Majesty who is practicing archery?
Noble Prince Guo came to visit.
His Lordship hunted game with His Majesty.
The veritable Noble Prince.
Vermilion told me that His Majesy pretended
to be Noble Prince Guo when he met you in the garden.
Now we get to see the real person.
His Majesty is an excellent archer.
It was Noble Prince Guo.
His Majesty was full of praise for His Lordship's archery skills.
Noble Prince Guo is known
for his achievement in the four arts.
It's a surprise that he excels at archery as well.
Ma'am, you'll discover His Lordship's
incredible versatility as you stay longer in the palace.
Xiao-Xiazi, you should bring back
the pigeons immediately.
And please inform His Majesty that I will pay respect
to him when he returns to the Governance Hall.
Allow me to take my leave.
I remember it was father who taught you archery.
Your Majesty's archery shifu was
the greatest baturu [Machu warrior].
My dull mind, however, didn't learn much from father.
What barturu taught was archery skills;
what father gave was parental love.
Father took a greater liking to you.
"Before heaven bestows great responsibilities upon a man,
it frustrates his spirit and will."
I ended up being a useless person
because of father's indulgence.
You've had a long day.
You should go have some rest.
I shall return to the Governance Hall.
His Majesty is leaving.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Good, you're here.
Prince XVII, with all his might, managed to
acquire half a catty of "snow-grown greens".
It is well worth the effort.
You should try it.
You Majesty seems to be in a great mood.
I heard that the "snow-grown greens" can only
be found on precipices in the farthest north.
There are hardly more than ten trees
of the kind all around the world.
Nourished by the snow,
the tea has a refreshingly icy taste.
What efforts must His Lordship have devoted!
- Xiao-Xiazi.
- Yes.
On top of that, he even made the effort
to send me the tea on such a blazing day.
The thought matters more than the gift itself.
His Majesty was concerned about the costs
if he receives the tea every year.
While His Lordship is a thoughtful person,
Your Majesty thinks for the long term.
Lady Sourire, you hit the nail on the head.
I learnt that Your Majesty had just
had an enjoyable hunt with His Lordship.
I wonder where His Lordship is.
His Lordship must have heard of your supernal beauty,
so he has to avoid meeting you.
I am immensely flattered.
Your Majesty need not think of an excuse for him.
His Lordship must have known that
I look like Wuyan, the ugly woman from Qi.
So he had to escape before I come.
Did you hear that?
If she looked like Wuyan,
what would the other concubines look like?
Sourire was just joking.
Have some tea.
This is veritable good tea.
It has a refreshing taste and aroma.
What a thoughtful gift from His Lordship!
I was told that when Your Majesty first met Sourire,
you made her believe that you were Prince XVII
and enjoyed music with her in the garden.
That led to your happy relationship today,
which is so romantic a tale in the palace.
How did you know of such a private affair?
You must have heard it from His Majesty.
I didn't say anything.
Qinmo had an attentive ear to have heard the story.
In that case, Prince XVII is the
matchmaker for Your Majesty.
Prince Matchmaker is renowned
for his unrestrained talent.
Many a girl from the most distinguished families
admires and desires His Lordship.
Sourire, I believe you must have heard of
His Lordship in your maiden years.
I was living an isolated life before the Selection,
and held in quarantine after I moved in.
I never had a chance to hear about His Lordship.
Your Majesty is a laureate in literature,
and most considerate to the concubines.
I wonder if Your Majesty did the same
to approach Lady Cao.
Wenyi must be feeling hungry at this time.
Allow me to go and see to her lunch.
All right.
Wenyi is still crying a lot lately.
Ask Dr Jiang what the problem is
the next time he visits you.
Certainly, I will report yo Your Majesty after that.
This zither was treasured by Consort Dowager Serein.
I was craving for zither music before you arrived.
But Lady Cao was just aptly like
her name Qinmo [a quiet lyre].
She didn't play well.
I shall send for Meizhuang.
She is a brilliant zither player.
Meizhuang is able to play faultlessly,
but her music is somewhat emotionless.
Emotionless music is dull
however good a zither plays it.
Will you play the zither for me.
With pleasure, Your Majesty.
So crisp and clear is the sound of the zither!
A cup of tea with zither as wind ruffles the water.
Such is a pleasure in life.
Will you play the fist verse of The Mountain Life.
I disappointed Your Majesty.
I hope I did not incur ridicule for my poor playing.
The playing was fine.
You were simply abstracted.
You did not devote all your heart to the zither.
I do beg Your Majesty's pardon
for my failure to commit to the music.
It was your first time playing the zither.
I understand that you were unacquainted with it.
But I have another question in mind.
Your love for me, I can clearly perceive.
But I was wondering when you began to feel love for me.
What I see is the person now sitting before me
regardless of his name or title.
What do you mean?
When Your Majesty, in the name of His Lordship,
extended your appreciation for my music in the garden,
I kept a respectful distance
even though I admired your flair.
After disclosing your identity,
Your Majesty took greater care of me
and treated me differently from the other concubines.
That is why I not only see Your Majesty
as the monarch, but also as my husband.
If I must tell Your Majesty the exact time,
it was when Your Majesty helped me out
when I was cornered by Yu in the garden.
I was utterly flustered at that moment.
While it was as easy as lifting a finger for Your Majesty,
in my eyes, Your Majesty was my savior.
I was just asking.
I hope Your Majesty would allow me to finish.
This might be a capital offence to Your Majesty.
I do revere you as the emperor,
but I regard you more as my loving husband.
I have always known that.
That is why I hold you dear to my heart.
Huan Huan, I was having undue suspicions.
Please don't blame me.
Si Lang.
My Lady, do you feel that someone revealed
your personal anecdote to Lady Cao?
It is just a doubt that I have.
There's no evidence.
(sigh) But only people closest to you would know such a tidbit.
I wasn't aware of it until today.
I believe Vermilion was the only witness in the garden.
But she is a dowry maid of yours, My Lady.
I know.
But I have confidence in Vermilion
after all these years living with her.
Yes, indeed.
She will never collude with Cao Qinmo against me.
I agree, My Lady.
Vermilion is a straightforward girl.
She might have brought it up to someone else.
But her unintentional words fell on a purposeful ear
so that the tidbit was passed on to Lady Cao.
That might be the only way to explain it.
It was fortunate that His Majesty trusted me.
Otherwise, I would be a goner
in face of the repeated rumor.
Absolutely.
Above all else, you've earned His Majesty's trust, My Lady.
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
At Your Majesty's behest, I have instructed the
Imperial Kitchen to reduce the food ration for every palace
and increase the use of vegetables.
Very well. I must set an example
as His Majesty requires frugality in the harem.
Certainly.
As for the highest-ranking concubines,
Consort Fleur and Consort Astuce,
they will have to have the same ration as mine
so that the other concubines may willingly follow suit.
That is a great idea, Your Majesty.
It was not my idea.
It was Lady Shen who brought it up to His Majesty.
I must not take the credit for her kind thought.
Your Highness, I brought you
desserts from the Imperial Kitchen.
It's all right to have less desserts,
but they should at least make the crab puffs for me!
The kitchen staff said that crab meat
is too expensive in the summer.
They will stop making such desserts
at the Empress's command.
They have already halved the daily ration.
What's all this small-mindedness with the desserts?
(huff) Your Highness, please don't be mad.
The Summer Palace is not as well-provided as home.
The Empress is always stingy.
You can count the concubines here on one hand.
How much can we possibly consume?
We've been having vegetarian meals all day.
Needle mushroom salad after smashed cucumbers.
I didn't even see a single piece of meat!
My appetite is already suppressed by the summer heat.
Now I don't even have to eat!
I learnt that it is the same with the Empress's palace.
It was all Lady Shen's idea. She suggested
to His Majesty that we halve the food ration.
She's not yet in the place to manage the palace.
But doesn't she know how to rule?
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Distribute some money among the servants.
They deserve to eat well on such a hot day.
Lunar made me some prune tea.
It tastes better than what the Imperial Kitchen makes.
You should try it!
You forgot that I don't like sour food, didn't you?
Oh, sorry about that.
In that case, I'll have yours.
My Lady, you've had four or five servings already.
It might cause stomach pain.
All right then.
I just couldn't help drinking it on a hot day.
Poria is very good at making prune tea.
Who is Poria?
She was sent to serve My Lady in the Summer Palace.
Princess Wenyi will have her
first birthday on the 19th of next month.
His Majesty wishes to hold a grand celebration for her.
His Majesty has been seeing Lady Cao
a lot lately because of Wenyi.
She has been complacent for
being unaffected by Consort Fleur.
I heard about what happened the day before last.
She aroused grave suspicion of you in just a few words.
That is not a person to be underestimated.
Fortunately, His Majesty trusted me.
(sigh) Whatever place we now hold in His Majesty's
affection, it is not secure until we have a child.
Consort Fleur is one good example.
Without a child, she was
deprived of her authority overnight.
It would be futile to live an infertile life in the palace.
You are different from them.
Well, I am different from them.
His Majesty still talks to Consort Astuce
for she is the mother of the Third Prince.
Same with Lady Cao and Attendant Joie, whose
daughters are loved just as dearly by His Majesty.
The mother of a beloved child will
always be cherished by His Majesty.
Otherwise, a concubine will be forgotten after
the ephemeral affection from His Majesty.
By my calculations, it has been almost a year
since your first service to His Majesty.
I wonder ... why it is taking so long.
His Majesty hardly visits the harem.
Now I have even less time to see His Majesty
as I'm helping Her Majesty with the palace affairs.
(sigh)
After all, I must harbor bad luck.
Nonsense, it has nothing to do with luck.
Consort Fleur won incomparable favor from His Majesty
even if she didn't have a child.
We'll have so many children to fill the room with joy.
Put your mind at ease.
Can I talk to you heart-to-heart?
While pregnancy seems to depend on the will of Heaven,
[the Heaven represents the emperor]
people propose when Heaven disposes.
There is something we can do.
It seems to me that
the visit of His Majesty is all that matters.
What is there for us to do?
May I help you, doctor?
My name is Liu Ben. I'm here for the routine checkup
when Dr Jiang is away for a family funeral.
I hope you won't mind waiting for a while.
My Lady is talking to Lady Sourire.
Certainly.
With a carrot and stick, Dr Jiang
finally agreed to give me this prescription.
Following his instructions,
you are guaranteed to have a boy.
You should start as well.
Who is this Dr Jiang?
Who else can it be?
Jiang Cheng.
He's an expert in gynecology.
Jiang Cheng?
His younger brother, Jiang Shen,
is the doctor of Lady Cao.
Exactly.
Can we trust his prescription?
Don't worry.
I have done an extensive background check on him.
They are half brothers whose mothers are on competitive terms.
Because of this, they clash like fire and water.
That is why I trust him.
In addition,
I looked into many medical books
before I decided to use the prescription.
But I can't help feeling skeptical.
I'll send for Dr Wen to look at the prescription.
Vermilion, can you make the trip
to see if Mr Wen is on shift today?
If so, bring him here right away.
My Lady, Lord Protector Sun is gravely ill.
Dr Wen was sent away to attend to him.
He will stay there until Lord Sun gets better.
When did Dr Wen go?
Yesterday afternoon.
Dr Wen left on short notice
because it was an emergency.
How coincidental!
Not to worry, I've had two doses already.
I trust it is fine.
You don't have to summon a brigade for it.
Yes, exactly.
I saw a doctor ready and waiting outside.
I shall go since a doctor is visiting you.
I'll see you tomorrow.
Vermilion.
Your servant bows in respect before his mistress.
Your doctor bows in respect before you, My Lady.
I don't remember seeing you before.
This is my first visit to you, My Lady.
You seem to have a Jizhou accent.
I was transferred from Jizhou just a few days ago.
How serendipitous!
I'm from Jizhou as well.
I feel deeply honored, My Lady.
Poria, brew a pot of Longjing tea.
Certainly.
Princess Wenyi will be one year old in half a month.
The first birthday is well worth a grand celebration.
Even though we are not in the palace, His Majesty
wishes to have it as memorable as possible.
I have instructed the Household Department
to prepare for the occasion.
I thank Your Majesties.
Wenyi and I will be eternally thankful.
We are grateful for your contribution to the family.
Please don't thank us.
It would be a blessing if
His Majesty has imperial heirs in plenty.
I hope every one of you can share the
responsibility to expand the family.
Yes, Your Majesty.
While we don't have many imperial heirs,
we get one more when we come to the Summer Palace.
Consort Fleur, don't speak of such a taboo subject.
I don't care if that's a taboo to you.
How can the son of a humble maid
be counted as an imperial heir?
While the Fourth Prince is the son of a humble maid,
he is still the son of His Majesty
and the brother of the Third Prince.
(snort) How does he deserve to?
All right. Why did you have to bring it up?
We all have been living with His Majesty for a long time.
Even if you don't care about it being a taboo,
do you not care how His Majesty would feel?
Pardon me, Your Majesty.
You should spend more time helping
the Third Prince with his studies.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
The Third Prince has been
working into late night recently.
Very well, he must set
a good example as the eldest son.
Handwork doesn't necessarily
make him better than a low-born.
I heard the Fourth Prince reciting
poems by the lake on my way here.
He sounded so much better than his brother.
Eh? Your Majesty, I can't help wondering who
has been taking care of the motherless boy.
Why does he seem to be smarter
than his distinguished brother?
You ...
Don't forget your manners, Consort Fleur.
In principle, you should be promoted
when your daughter is one year old.
But we are on a tight budget
while faced with the likely outbreaks of wars.
His Majesty wishes to hold a
glorious ceremony for you afterwards.
I believe you would't mind the delay.
Certainly, Your Majesty.
I am truly grateful for His Majesty's generosity.
But my humble existence does not
deserve His Majesty's heavenly grace.
All I wish is to always see joy and peace
abide in Your Majesties.
His Majesty appreciates your understanding.
He sends Wenyi a pair of jade ruyi to place the pillow on.
I will have it sent to your palace.
I thank Your Majesty.
Madam Autumn!
Good heavens! Why did you come here?
Where are your maids?
They don't care about me.
May I pay respect to Her Majesty?
Her Majesty is having a nap.
May I pay respect to His Majesty?
You should go when His Majesty summons you.
Excuse me.
Escort the Fourth Prince back to his residence.
Your Majesty, peeling lotus seeds
might hurt your finger nails.
His Majesty likes lotus seeds.
I wish to do it for him.
I will make lotus seed sweet soup for His Majesty.
Your love for His Majesty is more precious than gold.
But love is not as important as having a child.
Your Majesty, the Fourth Prince dropped by.
Why did he come here?
He wished to see His Majesty.
Forget it. He'll only make a nuisance of himself.
His Majesty would be displeased.
The Fourth Prince is too young
to have lost his birth mother.
Are you suggesting that I foster the Fourth Prince?
I thought the Fourth Prince
might be an option for Your Majesty.
But he is the least favored child.
What's the use of fostering him?
It's all right.
The hot and humid weather caused pimples.
Look, here's one, and here's another.
Don't worry, that increases the rosiness of your fair skin.
Now that your pimples are gone,
you start to make fun of mine.
All right, I'll stop it.
I can give you the anti-acne formula if you like.
It was offered by Dr Liu Ben,
who happens to be from Jizhou as well.
That is how my pimples were cured.
But I've never heard of this doctor.
He was just transferred from Jizhou.
He is an experienced doctor.
It is always nice to know
someone from your hometown.
Is he trustworthy?
I think so.
That's good.
When it comes to selecting servants,
character matters more than skills.
We must ensure that they have a clear background.
I agree.
Now that we both have a trusted doctor,
we will have more assurance in the palace.
Did you ask him to review Dr Jiang's prescription?
Yes, he said it is a perfect formula.
For real?
Peace to Your Highness.
I thought that there was only
the three of us in the garden.
You two seem to be enjoying the day as well.
It's nice that the weather is not as hot today.
I'm glad that you are here, Sourire.
I was going to visit you later.
I wonder if there is anything I can do for you.
I wish to apologize for
my improper remark the other day.
I heard that it caused misgivings to His Majesty.
I had no intention of doing that.
I must ask for your forgiveness today.
It was nothing like that, Lady Cao.
I simply had a bit of banter with His Majesty.
It wasn't not a big deal.
His Majesty is very fond of Lady Sourire.
Bantering with His Majesty is all too common for her.
But it would be such a big deal if it was someone else.
How can we possibly compare to Lady Sourire?
We have to first see His Majesty
before we can banter with him.
All right, all right.
We shouldn't be standing here for a talk.
Please come to my place.
I have prepared tea and snacks
to apologize to Lady Sourire.
And I invited Consort Astuce
and Attendant Joie for this purpose.
I humbly wish that Lady Sourire would not decline.
Lady Shen,
I've always admired your talent for playing the zither.
"An entertaining host attracts visitors."
But I am such an inept hostess.
Lady Shen, I hope you don't mind
helping me keep my guests with your music.
I'm grateful for your invitation.
My Lady, the prune tea has been cooled down.
You brought on the refreshing tea
after the greasy dishes.
What a gracious hostess we have!
Aiyo, what is wrong, Lady Shen?
I probably had too much jade aspic than I should.
I'm feeling a little sick.
Sick?
But you were all right right now.
Have you been feeling nauseous recently?
I haven't been eating well due to the summer heat.
Ah?
Is that ... because of pregnancy?
Have you menstruated this month?
I ...
Aiya, we are sisters.
- You can tell us.
- Exactly.
It's been late for more than half a month.
She's very likely to be with child.
Your Highness, what do you think?
Eh? In addition to feeling sick,
have you been feeling indolent lately?
And ... and having a craving for spicy food?
Xiao-Weizi, send for the doctor.
Please bring Dr Liu Ben.
Grace to Your Majesty.
You were the first one to arrive, nonetheless.
Is it true that Lady Shen is with child?
I was just informed to come here as well.
I have ordered the Attendance Registry
to be sent here immediately.
- Let's go inside.
- Certainly.
His Majesty the Emperor.
- Peace to Your Majesties.
- Sit down, sit down.
Is it real?
Doctor, can you confirm whether Lady Shen is pregnant?
Congratulations to Your Majesty and Lady Shen!
Lady Shen has been pregnant for over a month.
Very well. All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Autumn, bring the Attendance Registry.
Your Majesty.
(Palace of Universal Happiness, Lady Shen,
9 pm to 3 am, March 16th)
It was a good date.
Who are the personal maids of Lady Shen?
Your Majesty.
You must take the best care of
Lady Shen as her personal maids.
Report to me daily on her diet and health.
Yes.
The Empress is as meticulous as always.
Your Majesty, now that Lady Shen is with child,
we must select an imperial doctor to attend to her.
Your Majesty, this is Dr Liu Ben.
He is a reliable doctor,
and he is from Jizhou as well.
I have confidence in him.
Just as well.
Nothing matters more than your health.
You must ensure the best care of yourself.
I will.
My apologies to Your Majesties.
I forgot to serve Your Majesties tea all this time.
I was overwhelmed with joy.
I feel like a drink as well.
Would you like something to drink?
I spilled some prune tea earlier.
I have a craving for it now.
Quick, quick.
Yes, of course! There is plentiful prune tea.
I will have prune tea sent to you every day if you like!
It is very kind of you to offer, Lady Cao.
Can someone bring on the prune tea?
I hope Your Majesties will like the prune tea as well.
Lady Sourire doesn't enjoy sour food.
Please sweeten her tea.
Yes, of course.
I thank Your Majesty.
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.